<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The protestation of the most high and mightie Prince Frauncis, bothe sonne and brother of King, Duke of Allenson and of Eureux, Earle of Droux, &amp; of Perche &amp;c. Liuetenant General for the King in all his countries and dominions, protector of the libertie of the crowne of Fraunce, oppressed by the straungers. Translated out of frenche into English, and newely imprinted.</title>
            <title>Protestation de treshaut et trespuissant prince François duc dÁlençon. English</title>
            <author>Anjou, François, duc d', 1554-1584.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1575</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01197</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11311</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118480</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853687</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853687</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19081</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01197)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19081)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1202:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The protestation of the most high and mightie Prince Frauncis, bothe sonne and brother of King, Duke of Allenson and of Eureux, Earle of Droux, &amp; of Perche &amp;c. Liuetenant General for the King in all his countries and dominions, protector of the libertie of the crowne of Fraunce, oppressed by the straungers. Translated out of frenche into English, and newely imprinted.</title>
                  <title>Protestation de treshaut et trespuissant prince François duc dÁlençon. English</title>
                  <author>Anjou, François, duc d', 1554-1584.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>T. Vautrollier],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1575.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Protestation de treshaut et trespuissant prince François duc dÁlençon.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Wars of the Huguenots, 1562-1598 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19081:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:19081:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 71 -->
            <p>THE <hi>PROTESTATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON OF THE MOST HIGH AND MIGHTIE PRINCE FRAVNCIS, bothe Sonne and Brother of King, Duke of Allenſon and of Eureux, Earle of Dreux, &amp; of Perche &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LIVETENANT GENERAL FOR THE KING IN ALL HIS COVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treis and dominions, Protector of the libertie of the Crowne of Fraunce, oppreſſed by the ſtraungers.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of frenche into En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, and newely imprinted. 1575.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19081:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 72 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:19081:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 72 -->
            <head>THE PROTFSTA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION OF THE MOST HIGHE and mightie Prince Frauncis, bothe Sonne and Brother of King, Duke of Allenſon &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>RAVNCIS, both ſonne &amp; brother of a King, Duke of Allenſon, firſt Peere of Fraunce &amp;c. To all men whome it ſhall appertaine, Greeting. Knoweye that we being true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aduertiſed and informed, that of the obſeruation of lawes dependeth the conſeruation of all Realmes and Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipps, and by that meanes peace gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth and is intertained among the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, So whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are not kept in the puritie that our anceſtorshaue leaft the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs, and that they ſeeme to weaken and decaye, and be as it were dead and buried, The ſubiectes being imhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19081:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 73 -->do licence, diſpence, and eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giue them ſelues to all diſſolutnes: vvhich doeth cauſe oftentimes ciuil vvarres. And finally the deſtruction &amp; ouerthrowe of great realmes and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vvelthes: if in time it be not reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died by the diuine goodnes of God, vvhich doth raiſe (whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it pleaſeth him) excellent and mightie perſonnes to vvithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nie of thoſe vvhich ſeeke not but to bring all things to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, onely to make them ſelues riche, (at vvhoſe coſt ſoeuer it be) of the blood and ſvveate of the poore: or els to ſeaſe them ſelues of the ſaid realmes &amp; Lordſhips, as we may eaſely leame, by the ruynes and decayes of infinit flori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g kingdomes, that by theſe like mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes haue ended, vvhich ought to be an exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple to al true frencheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for to prick them forevvard to ſet vp againe the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient lavves, and to let and vvithſtande (euerie one according to the abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19081:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 73 -->vvhich God hath giuen vnto him) that it may not fall into the hands of thoſe vvhich of long time haue ſought for it. And for to bringe their purpoſe to paſſe, doe nouriſhe and maintaine the diſſentions vvhich vve ſee at this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, coulouring their dealings with the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſie that is in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: which they vvoulde be right ſorie to ſee it pacified, as it is euidently ſeene, and vvell kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vven by the things paſſed, to the intent they may colour the better the taxes, impoſts, and ſubſidies vvhich they doe daily inuent, and gather in the Kinges name vpon the poore people, the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, and the Clergie, vnder pretence to pay his debtes: tending onely to the vvealthe of fevve perſonnes almoſt all ſtraungers, vvhich rule the King, and occupie the chiefe places, &amp; offices of this realme againſt the lawes of the ſame. All the which enterpriſes vve coulde not vvell lyke of, and therfore
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19081:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 74 -->haue bene calumniated, and euill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to the Kingour moſt deare Lord and Brother, and for this cauſe in great daunger of our life, and kept as euery one knoweth, which thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs we haue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, hoping that the King vvoulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy ſuch miſeries, &amp; ſuffer no lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to be abuſed of ſo many men, and that he ſhould knovve our innocencie. But ſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the vvounde to vvaxe daily vvorſe and vvorſe, and no perſon to be more vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvorthily vſed then vve. And that ſo many Princes, Lordes, Gentelmen, and Eccleſiaſticall perſones, Citizens, and burgeſſes, had their eyes fixed on vs, ſtretching forth their hands and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring our aide. We being ouercome vvith their prayers, and partaker of their miſeries reſolued (all feare of death ſet a ſide, vvhich vvas neare to enſue) to atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt to get out of the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie that vve vvere in, to take the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blicke cauſe in hande, and to withſtande
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19081:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 74 -->the vvicked &amp; pernitious cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſells of the perturbators of this Realme, in vvhich atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt God hathe ſo fauored vs that the xvi. day of Septe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber vve arriued in this our tovvn of Dreux, vvhere many lords Gentelme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; others, aſvvel of the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie as of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of this realme haue repaired vnto vs: to whome we haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that our vvil &amp; intentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was not to take vpon vs, or to atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt in any vviſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the authoritie of the King our ſaid Lord and Brother, the vvhich vve deſire to preſerue &amp; increaſe vvith all our po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vver. But onely to employ vs vvith all our forces, yea not to ſpare our life and goodes for to put out, and driue avvay all the perturbators of the publicke reſt: to purſue by lavve and iuſtice all ſuche ſpoyles, theftes, murthers, and ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſo abominably, and againſt all right and reaſon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted in the oppen ſight and knovvledge of all men, to deliuer ſo many Lordes Gentelmen and others
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19081:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 75 -->co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted priſoners, or wrongfully bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed &amp; vvithout cauſe: to reſtore them againe (and all other honeſt men) to their goodes and liuings, eſtates, and honours: to aboliſh all taxes, ſubſidies &amp; impoſts ſet vpon the poore people by the malice and ſuggeſtion of ſtrangers, againſt the auncient Lavves &amp; ſtatutes of this Realme. To maintai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and Cleargie in their auncient pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledges, freedoms, &amp; liberties. And ſo, to ſtabliſh in Fraunce, a good, firme, &amp; ſtable peace. And to bring theſe things to paſſe, vve doe not meane to vſe any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes, but ſuche as our prediceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors haue done, &amp; that haue bene acuſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med at all times in this Realme, vvhen it hathe bene queſtion of reformation of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and iuſtice: vvhich are the tvvo pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cipall ſtayes of all Monarchies, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore againe the Realme to his former floriſhing ſtate, dignity &amp; libertie: that is by a generall and free aſſemblie of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19081:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 75 -->three eſtates of this Realme, being called &amp; appointed to be kepte in a ſure &amp; free place, from the vvhich all ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers ſhal be excluded. Proteſtinge before God (vvhome vve call to our aide &amp; helpe, and vvho vve be aſſured vvill guide our enterpriſes) that vve are not herein moued nor leadde throughe deſire of priuate reuenge (althoughe vve haue iuſt occaſion ſo to doe, for the greate vvronges done vnto vs) nor yet of highnes or deſire to commaund more then vve doe, or then to vs ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaineth. Being pleaſed and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (as we haue good occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) vvith the goodes, auctoritie, and greatnes, that we haue of Godds grace, &amp; of his benignity hauing apoynted vs to be borne the ſon of a Kinge, and ordained vs the ſeconde perſon of this Realme. That if it happen (as God forbid) to call vs before ſuche time as we may ſee the ende and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of this ſo holy an enterpriſe, we
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19081:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 76 -->ſhall thinke vs moſt happy to haue (for the ſame) beſtovved our life, which doth concerne the ſeruice of God and of the Kinge, the freedome and libertie of the Nobilitie and of the Cleargie, the reſt &amp; vnburdening of the people, and the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie of the country. And for to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all lettes, and to reconcyle the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of naturall Frenchemen, vve haue taken &amp; do take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in to our protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ſafe keping, aſvvell of the one re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion as of the other. Praying &amp; exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in the name of God, to behaue them together one with an other as bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, frendes, and fellowe Citezens: and not to prouoke one an other by iniuries or otherwiſe: Vntill that by the generall eſtates, and aſſembly of counſil order be taken for religion, and to permitte and let euery one enioye the exerciſe of the ſame. Praying all Kinges, Quenes, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Potentates, comon wealthes &amp; all other neighbours, alies, and confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19081:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 76 -->of this Realme &amp; Crovvne to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, ayde, &amp; helpe vs in this ſo holy and laudable enterpriſe: and to haue none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther opinion of vs, then that vvhich we declare and teſtifie by this preſent Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation. Praying alſo all Princes, Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, Gentlemen, Citizens, Towneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, &amp; all other ſubiects of the crovvne, to repaire to vs, to accompanie &amp; helpe vs vvith victualles, armour, money, and others their abilities &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities, that through their faulte and negligence the executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſo highe an enterpriſe be not differred; &amp; the peace letted. Declaring only thoſe to be our ennemies vvhich by force ſhall reſiſte and ſeeke to vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande our enterpriſe: And our frendes thoſe which ſhall runne vpon them.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at Dreux, <date>the xvij. day of September. 1575.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Subſcribed Francis.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19081:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 77 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:19081:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 77 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
